Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 22; A.L. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Introducing Mr. Perry, a great ship-builder, who desires Franklin's advice about placing his sons in France for a few months. English politics; Mr. [William] Pitt's attitude towards Ireland; his taxes on manufacturers. Dr. [Richard] Price's abridged translation of the Testament of M. Fortuné Ricard; reasons for thinking it will do good. Several schemes for reducing the national debt submitted by Dr. Price to Mr. Pitt on condition that he examine them himself. Sends him a second bottle of [Alexander] Blackrie's Lixivium.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 22; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning his application for a passage for Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 23; A.L.S. 2p.; La Luzerne, Chevalier de
    Introducing Messrs. Joseph Combes and d'Ejean, rich merchants of Languedoc, who intend establishing a commercial house in America; advantage of such a trade; recommends them to Franklin's kindness and protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Groc. F Deumié. L'Orient
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 25th ult., together with other papers relative to his vessel "L'Aimable Elizabeth"; wishes to send him more documents in order that he may get at the root of the matter; the sailors of the "Nancy" accused of taking away many things from the French ships; begs Franklin to continue assisting him in this unfortunate affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Laurens, Jean Frederic. Treptow on-the-Riga
    Requesting him to send the enclosed letter to Henry Laurens, former President of Congress. Takes a keen interest in Franklin's philosophical work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Bon de Corcelles, Pierre. London
    Expects to sail for Philadelphia in three weeks, on board the ship "Eagle"; begs Franklin to forward to London the desired letter of recommendation. Lacks the money necessary to pay his passage, and the time to procure it from home; begs Franklin to assist him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 29; A.L.S. 4p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Never received Franklin's favor of Nov. 24, 1784, until the 25th inst.; complaints he has made to the post-office. Letters he has written to the Count de Florida Blanca in favor of several Americans at Havana who complain of the oppression and injustice of the Spanish Governor; has received no satisfactory reply. Court ceremonies he has attended; marriage of the Infanta; necessary expenses of his life in Spain; has been obliged to spend his savings; desires Franklin's advice about writing to Congress on this subject. Question of America forming a defensive alliance with Genoa and Venice against the piratical states.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 29; A.L.S. 2p.; D'orbelin, Mme ------. Paris
    Storm of jealousy aroused by her successful experiments with mercury; assertion of her rivals that the fixation of mercury is a chimerical project; applies to Franklin, who witnessed her experiment, for a testimonial of her work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Brun, Abbé Joseph André. Paris
    Copies of Le Triomphe du Nouveau Monde which Franklin promised to send to their destination; begs him to open the second volume and examine the loose leaves; these could not be made a part of the volume without compromising the author. Dissertation on marriage and divorce. [7p.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 March 31; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Williamos, Charles. Paris
    Sending Franklin two spermacetti candles, the only ones he has left.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Windisch-Grätz, comte de. Brussels
    Expects to visit Paris shortly; looks forward with the greatest eagerness to making his acquaintance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    No further news from Morocco; rumor that Spain is to send an Ambassador Extraordinary with presents to the Emperor; report that the negotiations for peace with the privateers of Algiers have proved unsuccessful. Death of Mr. [James] Hartwell at a moment when he would certainly have had his liberty. Sends him the work of Bayer. Begs for a bust of Dr. Franklin. Prospect of Dr. Franklin returning to America. Desires to know whether Congress has done justice to his namesake.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; St. Maux, Viel de
    Sent Franklin his Letters sur l'Arcitecture; desires a copy sent to the [American Philosophical] Society at Philadelphia, as a token of his regard; expects to publish more of his researches in the progress of science and art; would be glad to enter into a correspondence with the Society on this subject.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 5; Printed L.S. 1p.; Brevost, ------. Paris
    Announcement of the next meeting of the Maison Philantropique.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; D'orbelin, Mme ------. Paris
    Depressed by Franklin's silence; begs for the loan of twenty-five louis, which she promises to repay in three months.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 5; Engraved N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 6; L.S. 2p.; Beyer, -----. Paris
    His promise to give a name to the instrument he has constructed; sends him a small snuff-box which he has made for him as a token of his regard.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 8; L. 2p.; -----, -----. Malago
    A proclamation has been issued for assembling the seamen belonging to the district for the purpose of manning the gunboats. The Emperor of Morocco, it is said, is to join the expedition with an army headed by Spanish officers. The three Spanish garrisons, Melillo, Penon, and Athusemas, are to be ceded to His Majesty and an exclusive trade to Barbary with Spain is to result from the alliance. Generals mentioned for the naval command, and land forces.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Jalheau, -----. Paris
    His parents unable to assist him further in his medical studies; desires, with Franklin's help, to go to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 12; D.S. 1p.; Vernon, William Jr. Paris
    An order to Dr. Franklin on his father for 840 livres.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 13; A.L. in 3d P. 3p.; Anisson, ----- le fils
    His hope of becoming a member of the Royal Academy of Sciences; his efforts and his successes in improving the art of printing; desires to place before the Society a new invention for preparing printed paper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Adams, John. Auteuil
    Thanking Franklin for his information of the packet's arrival; as yet has received no letters, public or private.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Sends several classics, as well as a copy of a bill of exchange for his endorsement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Steps taken for the release of the American vessel held at Morocco; Mr. Harrison's application for money to relieve their distresses. Treaty to be concluded between the Court of Spain and the Emperor of Morocco. The Princess of Brazil to set out shortly for Portugal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Philadelphia
    His high opinion of the utility of bathing; his plan to have a building erected in which different kinds of baths may be commodiously united; desires Franklin's opinion of the Russian vapor baths, as described in a paper by Dr. Sanchez. Wishes America would make a wise use of the advantages procured for her by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 18; Printed N.S. 1p.; Brevost, ------. Paris
    Announcement of a meeting of the Maison philantropique.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Barclay, David. London
    Glad of this opportunity to inquire after Franklin's health; the bearer is his worthy young friend, Benjamin Chew.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Dutartre, Madame Melin
    Reproaches him with forgetting her; for his penance demands a letter of recommendation to the President of Congress on behalf of the Comte de Poloresky and his brother, who desire a small grant of land in New Hampshire; the Marquis de la Fayette has given them two letters, but Franklin's is absolutely necessary. Refers to his friendship with Mme. Brillon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Rousseau, Jean. London
    No answer to his letter of December 24th; his situation more unfortunate than ever; in need of Franklin protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 19; Engraved N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Beauvilliers, Mme de
    Has supported herself by keeping a pension; begs Franklin to lend her sixteen louis, which she will repay in a year.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Baudin, N. Nantes
    Informed that Congress has established an order of chivalry as a recompense to those who have served America with honor and distinction; sets forth his claims to this Order of Cincinnatus.
    A.E. by Franklin. The gentleman has been misinformed; the Order of Cincinnatus is a mere convention among the officers of the American army, not approved of by any Government; has therefore no concern with it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Introducing Mr. [Charles] Long, Jr., whose father wrote the late history of Jamaica; Doctors [Richard] Price and [Joseph] Pricstley have just dined with him; talked of Franklin and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 22; L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre. Paris
    Sends the letter from the Inspector of Customs, who will forward the press ordered for the Royal Printing-House.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Lettsom, John Coakley. London
    Apologizing for the memoirs [of Dr. Fothergill] he sent Franklin, which are unworthy of their subject; difficulties in the way of his writing a more complete history. Reflections on the new spirit pervading Europe; the growing belief that freedom and independence are the true springs of industry and enterprise; the possible establishment in the future of a perfect Government.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Steinsky, François. Prague
    Sends him his volume of hymns and several papers on different subjects.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis. Paris
    Wishes Franklin to see his article on Indian corn before it is published.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 April 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Thompson, Thomas. Dover
    Glad he is pleased with the delivery of his newspapers; thinks M. Mouron, of Calais, would appreciate a line of approbation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Writes on behalf of the children of the late Lord Templeto[w]n, who desire to lay claim to twenty thousand acres of land belonging to their father, situated on the Susquehannah; will be much obliged for Franklin's advice and assistance; sends a letter on this subject [1p.] which he begs may be forwarded to Mr. [John] Jay in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Trinquesse, ----. Paris
    Begs Franklin's assistance in recovering from his lodger, M. [William] Vernon, [Jr.], the rent for the last eighteen months; wishes to avoid calling in the police.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 3; Engraved N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Delivet, ----. Paris
    Desires permission from the Marquis de Castries to print a prospectus of the equipment he wishes to send to Chesapeake Bay; the cargo he sent to Baltimore the previous year proved a great loss owing to the ignorance of the merchants as to the kind of goods in demand; thinks the prospectus will obviate this difficulty; begs Franklin's influence with the Minister.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Viny, Thomas. Tenterden
    Letter received from his son, Joseph Viny, concerning his endeavors to turn to account the "bent felloe-wheel"; splendid assistance of a man named Ovenden; good prospect of success; desire of Ovenden to make a trial with the wheel at Paris in connection with Joseph's younger brother; asks Franklin's advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Walter, John. London
    Describes the alterations he has made in the founts; heavy expenses attending this work; possibility of his receiving a gratuity for this improvement from the Court of France; names of books he is printing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Laugier, ----. Paris
    Sending Franklin two copies of his pamphlet, one for himself and the other for the principal academy in the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Prevented by his wife's illness from paying Franklin's grandson the attention he would have wished; sorrow for the loss of his wife. Letters received from Mr. [Henry] Laurens, who is busy collecting and arranging the crumbs the British troops have left him. His own estate in North Carolina to be confiscated unless some weighty interference takes place; hardly likes to ask such a favor of Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Arrival of the bust [of Dr. Franklin, for Sir Edward Newenham] which was put on board the "City of Dublin."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 9; Printed N. 1p.; Brevost, ------. Paris
    Announcing a meeting of the Maison Philantropique.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 9; L.S. 1p.; Castries, M de
    Concerning Mr. [William] Bingham, Agent for the United States at Martinique, being obliged to borrow from the French Government to meet the demands of American vessels; informed that this money has been refunded by Congress, but the dept to France is still unpaid; desires Franklin to take whatever measures he deems proper in this affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Guillot, -----. Paris
    Begging for a five minutes' audience in the interest of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 11; L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre
    Sending permit to enable Dr. Franklin to get Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson's English printing-press out of the custom house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 11; A.L.S. 1p; Grubb, J. L'Orient
    Mt. [Thomas] Barclay too ill at present to write; hopes in a few days to be able to set out for Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Carmichael, William. Aranjuez
    Enclosing the last advices received from Morocco; necessity of temporizing with the Prince until the sentiments of Congress are fully explained. Answer received to his letter to Congress respecting M. [Diegode] Gardoqui's mission; his conduct in this business approved.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 12; A.L. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Account of his business dealings with M. Renouard; refuses to admit him as his creditor. Glad that Franklin has gotten his release; question of his going home. Detained by pursuit of his debtor, Mr. [Philip] Moore. Commissions executed and people seen. Critical attitude of England towards America; fails to see her own faults. [Incomplete.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Hears that Franklin has obtained his recall; congratulations for his past work and good wishes for his future health and happiness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 13; A.L.S. Samuel Bard, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The New York Society for Promoting Useful Knowledge. New York
    Advising Franklin of his being chosen a member of the Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 14; A.L.S. 6p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Late acrostatic experiments in England; [Vincenzo] Lunardi's failure; [François] Blanchard has all the honors. Sir John Cambridge's assertion as to the rate at which a coal barge descends a stream, without sails or oars, in a dead calm. Account of the extremely youthful behavior of old General [James Edward] Oglethorpe. Saw at a bookseller's a translation of Cicero on Old Age with Dr. Franklin's name and picture on the title page; desires to know if he is really the author? Commissions executed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Explains why Mr. Orillard's memoir is falsely stated. Obliged to treat Mr. Gavrelle like all his other creditors. Information concerning Franklin's proposed passage to America. Obliged to go to Ireland in pursuit of [Philip] Moore.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Frankland, Richard. Dublin
    Introducing Mr. David Franks who goes to America on a visit to his uncle Mr. Carrol McNamara, of Virginia; Franklin's countenance and advice will be of the most essential service to him. Promises to show every courtesy in his power to any of Franklin's friends passing through Ireland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 18; A.L.S. 1p.; D'orbelin, Mme ------. Paris
    Begs for an audience to prove the possibility of rendering mercury a fusible metal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Brutelle, Charles Louis L'Héritier de
    Sending two copies of his work on Botany, one for Congress, the other for the [American] Philosophical Society at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Freeman, James. Rotterdam
    Introduced to Franklin by his wife's uncle, Dr. [John] Fothergill. Recommends Dr. [Solomon] Drown who is travelling through England and France with a view of learning anything new in physick; begs Franklin to overlook the shabbiness of the Doctor's apparel and assist him in any way possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 23; Printed N. 1p.; Brevost, ------. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Percival, Dr. Thomas. Manchester
    Franklin's election to their [Manchester Literary and] Philosophical Society. His tract on the Perceptive Powers of Vegetables. Franklin's flattering reception of his Moral and Literary Dissertations. Praise for Bishop Watson's tracts on the Evidences of Natural and Revealed Religion. Prospect of Franklin's revisiting England.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 180; Bigelow, IX, 120).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    His grief at hearing of Franklin's approaching departure. Bewails his money-losses. Sends two volumes of his Miscellanies in German for the [American] Philosophical Society; refers him to Le Bègue [de Presle] for two copies of the French work, dedicated to him; forwards copies of his dissertations on various subjects. Begs for late American newspapers. His desire to have all Franklin's philosophical papers. Thinks the scheme of M. Windisch-Grätz somewhat visionary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Introducing the Reverend Mr. Robinson, Mr. Hill's particular friend and a gentleman of character; concerned about Franklin's health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Defaÿ, ------. Orleans
    Desires to become a member of the Academy of Sciences; the previous year,sent them a work of his with a request to be made a corresponding member; since that time several vacancies have occurred; begs Franklin's influence on his behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 May 29; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Boufflers-Rouvrel, Marie-Charlotte-Hippolyte de Campet de Sanjon, comtesse de
    Sending him the promised book, which she begs him to return after its persual; hopes he has not forgotten her advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April to 1785 May; 181 p.; Coimet, -----
    Account for postage paid on Franklin's letters and charges for messages, errands, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1785 May]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Asking Franklin to appoint the day and hour when he can see M. [Jean Antoine] Houdon, the sculptor, relative to Mr. George Washington's statue.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1785. May]; A.L. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    Attitude of England; thinks the West India intercourse is held out upon, to serve as a concession at treating; ministerial politics. Hopes to write Franklin again cre be sets sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Valltravers, Johann Rodolph. Vienna
    Congratulating him on his long-wished for release from public duties. Reasons why Dr. Ingen Housz cannot accept Franklin's tempting offers to come to Philadelphia; no such obstacles in his own path; offers to accompany him. Translated into German Franklin's Instructions to those who think of Settling in America, but the censor would not permit its publication; desires to publish this and other papers in America, and devote his life to work of that kind.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 1; A.L.S. 1p.; La Briche, La Live de
    On applying to M. de la Ferté for the gondola, was informed of its sale the previous year. Shares with an entire nation the grief over Franklin's depature.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Windisch-Grätz, comte de. Brussels
    Congratulates himself on his interview with Franklin; packet forwarded to M. Ingen Housz. Offers his services in Belgium or Germany.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Price, Richard. Newington Green
    Case of a person named Bourne, a broker of London, who suddenly absconded, leaving a wife and four children; report of his being seen in Paris; begs Franklin, if the occasion offers, to inform him of his family's distress. Sent him copies of his pamphlet on the American Revolution. Library for the town of Franklin.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, X, 182; Bigelow, IX, 121).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Holker, Jean. Rouen
    Sending him a remedy which has been known to have wonderful results. Desires to know when Franklin will be in Rouen. Difficulties in the way of getting out the box of books, which lies among unclaimed stuff in the warehouses of the Farmers-General.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Dublin
    Arrival of the bust [of Dr. Franklin] in perfect condition; his and Lady Newenham's affectionate appreciation of such a gift. His trip to America postponed. Account of his proposed expedition in a balloon together with his eldest son and Mr. Potain; their intention to cross the Irish Channel; the whole affair to be kept a profound secret; their purpose to ascend masked and in fancy dress; if they succeed, they may possibly proceed to Paris; chance of his making food for the fishes; death has no terror for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Jarvis, James. Amsterdam
    If Franklin approves of the American ship spoken of, will make his proposals to the Captain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, Richard. Newington Green
    Begging him to render every assistance to Mrs. Bourne's brother, who has gone to Paris to find Mr. Bourne.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Barthélemy, -----. London
    The Comte d'Adhémar being still at Bath for his health, Mr. [William] Bingham has sent the writer Franklin's letter; will be delighted to aid Mr. Bingham in any way possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 June 6; A.L.S. 5p.; d'Anterroches, comtesse